This is Software Engineering Radio, the podcast for professional developers on the web at se-radio.net.
SE Radio is brought to you by the IEEE Computer Society and by IEEE Software Magazine online at computer.org/software.
[music]
Welcome to Software Engineering Radio. I'm your host Adi Narayan, and I'm here today with Martin Kleppmann.
Martin is an associate professor at the University of Cambridge working on local-first collaboration software and distributed system security.
He's the author of Designing Data-Intensive Applications, which is regarded as one of the foundational text for data engineering and distributed systems, and has sold more than 300,000 copies globally.
It's one of the most popular books on O'Reilly, and an updated version comes out sometime this year.
He's also one of the founders of the open-source library automerge, that allows developers to build collaborative apps where data merges automatically.
Prior to this, he founded two startups that were sold to LinkedIn and Redgate software.
Martin, welcome to Software Engineering Radio.
Hello, it's great to be here.
Yeah, a lot of engineers may be familiar with your really famous book on architecting big data systems, but your recent focus has been on local-first software, which we're going to be talking about today.
To begin, can you define what that term means and a little bit about its history?
Yeah, sure.
So, we were a few years ago working on this type of software where we wanted to combine the best of two different worlds.
Those two worlds are on the one hand old-fashioned pre-internet software from the 1990s.
You would just have some software, it would run on your computer, store its files on your computer, very simple model, which we now call local-only software.
But then we got cloud software, and with cloud software we get like real-time collaboration like in Google Docs and Figma and so on.
And that's super convenient, but now the files are no longer on your own computer anymore.
And so, if you ever got locked out of your account, for example, then all of your files are gone.
And so, local first is really trying to be the best of both of those two worlds, where we have the collaboration features that we know and love from cloud software,
but at the same time the data is also stored on your own computer locally.
And so, therefore, it's there when nobody can take it away from you.
I think you hit on a point there that these days collaborative software is so well entrenched, but it's the default is that it lives in the cloud.
Are there some sort of features when you say local first? It's more than just saving the data locally, right?
There's a lot more sort of principles that govern this.
What are those?
Yeah, so we realized that when you keep data locally, that opens up a bunch of really interesting advantages for software development, but also some challenges.
So, some of the advantages are, for example, that you can make the software work fine offline.
So, user can just keep editing the data in whatever way they like, regardless of whether they happen to have an internet connection right now.
And then, it'll just resync with the server and with your collaborators the next time you get an internet connection again.
But at the same time, while you're online, you can have real-time collaboration.
It also has performance advantages because if you click a button, then you don't have to wait for a network round trip before something happens.
So, the user experience can actually be really great because it means that the software just responds really well.
And finally, we found that from the point of view of the app developer,
it can actually be a much nicer software development model compared to writing cloud software because if you're writing cloud software, you first you're writing a front end,
which might be like JavaScript in a web browser, or maybe a mobile app.
But then, that has to sync via a server, and then you have to like define a REST API, or maybe you know, web socket protocol or something like that if you wanted it to be real-time.
And then, you have to write the back end.
There's just so much complexity in all these different levels of infrastructure that you have to build.
And so, part of the goal of local first software is actually also to simplify that infrastructure so that essentially you build only the front end and all of the data sync and back end is just abstracted away.
So even small teams can build you don't need to have like a dedicated back end group and front end group to make an app but a smaller group can just build the entire thing end to end. Exactly, that's the hope.
Yes, so right now there are some services providing back ends for local first software so you can then just build the front end and use a back end from some company.
What we would like to gradually move towards long term is to actually have open standards for these back ends so that you could then plug in a back end from many different providers and
just use whichever provider is the cheapest for example and then that way you're not bound to any one company for the back end but you have that flexibility and at the same time you can still build arbitrary software on top of it.
I think you covered a lot of ground there and let's dig into each of these things one by one.
First things, UX design.
So the fact that everything lives in the local machine means that the round trip is saved and the app should be more responsive. What does that look like?
You know, from a developer point of view, is the approach to UX design very different?
So the idea here is that you essentially only ever work with local data and any network communication just happens as a background process.
And that's then leads to these potentially really nice instant responses.
And there's been a bunch of apps that have used this very successfully.
Like Linear is an example of a tracker essentially that uses local first like architecture with a lot of local data in the browser and they found that
just the user experience advantages of being able to respond immediately like to user input when you use a click something or presses a key that that is really nice.
And you get a similar thing with say Google Docs or Figma where likewise you need every user interaction to instantaneously reflect on the screen.
You can't be waiting on the network round trip every time you hit a key in a text document.
That would just be really painfully slow to work with, especially if you're on a poor internet connection.
And so, this instant responsiveness of local-first software is like quite a nice UX benefit.
You mentioned one example there, Linear.
What does that app do for folks who may not have heard about it?
Oh, it's like a project management tool, like a bug tracker essentially.
So, to summarize, almost all of the data is stored locally.
So, it doesn't need to have any round trip to pull it, but it would have a cloud interface or a cloud server to sync it so that any other user when they're logging into my different devices able to pull that same notebook or the same the project, right? Exactly.
So, the way you implement this is with a sync engine.
So, a sync engine, you can think of like as a database replication tool essentially, but it replicates data between a database that's embedded on the user's own device.
So, for example, as like a local storage in their web browser, and a database that's on the server.
And any update that you make to the data on your own local device gets synced to the server whenever an internet connection is available.
And if another user has made an update to the database, that would typically go to the server and then be synced to the end user's client whenever an internet connection is available.
And so, this way you still get the real-time collaboration.
So, any change made by one user flow through the server and is synced to the other users with low latency.
And each user's local or client then re-renders the user interface based on those changes coming in over the network.
And that way you get this really nice real-time collaboration, but at the same time, if the internet connection is unavailable right now, well, then you're just working offline and you're just storing the data locally in your own local copy of the database.
I think the sync engine's really something interesting and we'll come back to that when we speak about the sort of the challenges around local first.
To give you a larger overview, are there certain design principles that govern pretty much all kind of local first software?
The sort of challenges that arise with it.
And so, one fundamental issue, if you allow people to work offline, is that well, they might make conflicting updates while offline.
This is something that software developers know very well from version control systems, obviously.
Like, anyone who's worked on a version control with Git in a team will know that like sometimes you get merge conflicts because different people have edited the same file on different branches.
And so, you get exactly that same pattern with other types of collaborative software, too.
And with like, local first per se doesn't prescribe any particular way of handling those kinds of conflicts.
In practice, we've had pretty good experiences using automatic merging algorithms.
And so, this automerge library that you mentioned uses some automatic merging algorithms so that if different users make edits to the same file, in most cases, we can automatically combine them into a consistent state.
But of course, like if people are literally editing the same sentence of a text document, we won't be able to merge those together, but the result probably won't be a grammatically accurate sentence.
And so, in those kind of situations, then it still becomes a UX problem of how we surface those kind of conflicts to the user and help them resolve it. Got it. Understood.
I think there was a paper out there of the manifesto that you published, and in that you had five core principles listed.
One was offline first, multi-device syncing, longevity that the data is always with you, conflict-free merging, and performance.
No spinners, everything in the same place, so things are faster. Do you still stand by those?
Are those sort of the five guiding principles for when somebody's trying to build something that's local first?
Yeah, so there were seven principles even in the original local first paper that we published.
So, one thing that we didn't really appreciate yet at the time is the simplification of the developer experience, actually.
So, in that paper, we focused very much on the user experience and the benefits for users, and that is still very much relevant and true, but we've come to since appreciate that also there are actually significant advantages for app developers as well.
And so, we've considered writing a follow-up piece at some point which elaborates on that, but we haven't got round to writing it yet. Got it.
What are some of those advantages to developers? Could you list a few?
It's mostly just not having to think about the network because thinking about the network is really annoying because every time you make a request over the network,
it might be that the user is on an unreliable coffee shop Wi-Fi and your request times out, and then you just have no idea what happened.
Like, did the data get to the server or not?
You just have no idea.
And so, like you're constantly writing tons of error handling code and trying to figure out what should you even do in the error case.
And the nice thing with using a sync engine is that the application code is only ever interacting with this local database that's embedded on the client,
and the whole distributed systems problem of syncing the data between that local copy and the servers and to other collaborators, that's just dealt with by the implementation of the sync engine.
So, of course, the network communication is still happening, but it's not happening in app code, and so app developers don't have to worry about it.
And so, essentially, we're pushing these distributed systems problems down into the infrastructure, and that can massively simplify the programming model.
I think you you hit a nerve there cuz as anyone who's built an app knows it, the amount of time you need to spend to just make sure that you know,
all kinds of network failures are taken care of and handled correctly without an unexpected failure or a you know, 404 screen.
It's so it's underrated, but it ends up taking so much time in any production project.
So, 100% agree with that.
To the point that you mentioned about the app only interacts with the local database,
is it correct to think of it as the app only interacts with the local database and as the connection is improved or if it comes out of an offline bubble,
the database gets synced with whatever the server or with another copy in the cloud and then the app adapts to any new information that's coming in. Is that accurate?
Yeah, exactly.
So, you know from say React for example,
it has this model where you can represent the user interface as a function of some model objects that exist in JavaScript and
typically those would be just some plain old JavaScript object and then if the data changes, you re-render the React components and then update the user interface based on that.
And so, we can use a very similar model for local-first software.
It's just that these model objects rather than just being these plain old JavaScript objects, we make that the state of the sync engine.
And so, whenever another user, another collaborator has made some update to the data,
that gets synced by the sync engine to the local copy and then you re-render the user interface using React or whatever component you're using and then that way the remote collaborators changes are directly reflected in the user interface.
And it's actually a really straightforward simple programming model where
you're not having to worry about the case of how you merge in the remote user's changes because the sync engine has done that merging already and all you need to do is re-render the UI.
And what is a sync engine merging with?
Is the expectation that there is a server or is it just a bunch of different users with apps on their devices?
Yeah, there are different sync engines and that take different approaches with regard to this.
So, there are some systems that assume that there is a server and so, it's a lot traditional cloud model in that sense.
But there are others that could work over a peer-to-peer network as well as a server and so,
Auto Merge is an example of a library that's designed for a decentralized use where if you want to use it with a single sync server, you could certainly do that,
but you could also use several servers side by side, for example.
Or, if it turns out that you are like on a local Wi-Fi with another device, but you don't actually have internet access,
or you maybe have Bluetooth connection between two devices or something like that, you can just use that local connectivity as well.
So, there's no assumption that you have to go via a remote server.
If you have some local connectivity or a peer-to-peer connection, that's perfectly fine as well.
So, all that Automerge requires really is some way of getting bytes from device A to device B,
and often relaying the bytes via a server is a convenient way of doing it, because we know how to run that kind of infrastructure, and peer-to-peer can sometimes be unreliable.
So, relying on peer-to-peer only is dangerous, but having peer-to-peer in there as an option that you can use alongside server-based sync, that's actually really empowering,
because it means that you might have a farmer on a remote field, and they just want to sync some data between their phone and their tractor, and they might not have cellular data connection where they are in some remote location.
They should still be able to sync that, because they have the two devices right next to each other.
And so, that's also part of what we actually wanted to enable with local first.
So, with local first, the local part doesn't actually refer just to local storage, but also to local networking.
So, if you have two devices that are physically close to each other, then they should just be able to communicate over a local network, and that should work just as well as going via a server.
That's so interesting, because these days we just take it for granted, right?
Like, even though if there are two people sharing a document, like say it's me and my wife editing the same document, for us to see our changes, the changes have to go to a server, I don't know, sitting in California or New York, and then come back to us.
And if that connection is not active, we can't even see each other's changes.
And we just take it for granted, but the fact is there are ways to, like you were saying, if we You say that devices can share information through whatever means possible, be it a peer-to-peer network or Bluetooth.
It gives you the same outcome without having to make those round trip journeys to a external server sitting somewhere else. Exactly.
And if you think about it, it's kind of ridiculous to send all of your data via AWS US East 1 if you have two devices sitting right next to each other.
There's really no need for them to go via some cloud.
We'll dig into some of these challenges a little bit later, but can you give us an idea of who's using it these days?
Like is it mostly folks making hobby projects or is it being applied in in any form in bigger and popular apps as well?
So there are increasing numbers of production users of these types of software as well.
So for Automerge, for example,
it's an open source project, but we have a bunch of companies commercially sponsoring it because these are companies using Automerge for their production products and
they want to make sure that it's a well-maintained good quality open source project and so they're voluntarily financially supporting the project like that.
I think many of them are pre-launched, so I'm not sure I can name them right now.
But there definitely people using this for production software and getting really good results out of it.
When we think about apps, say an app like an Excalidraw or WhatsApp for that matter, there are local-first elements there that I can notice.
The fact that the app can always work regardless of whether you have internet or not.
That like say in WhatsApp, you can read the messages even though there is no internet connection.
Or Excalidraw for that matter that saves all of the data locally and not on the cloud.
Do you see that there are mainstream apps using the principles, at least not all of them, but some of them because they're sort of almost common sense principles at this point?
Yeah, well, I would say Git, for example, which I mean, it's mainstream among software developers, maybe not mainstream amongst the general population.
But Git is totally local-first.
It has this property that you can create a commit while you're offline.
You can rewrite your local history while you're offline.
Um only for pushing and pulling do you need to be online. Everything else you can do offline.
All of the version control stuff you can look back at old versions of your repository and so on.
And that's something that we have come to take for granted as software developers because it's so useful to be able to do these kind of things locally on your laptop and it's just really fast as well.
And essentially what we're trying to do with local first software is to bring these capabilities that software developers have with Git,
to bring that to many other types of apps and many other different file types because the other big disadvantage of Git of course is there's no real-time collaboration and
you can't really put anything other than text files into it and get sensible merging behavior.
So, if you put a spreadsheet into Git, well, it'll just be a binary blob.
And if two people on different branches edit that spreadsheet, well, then good luck merging that.
And so, essentially what we want to do is have Git-like capabilities, but bring them to not just text files,
but spreadsheets and graphics apps and issue trackers and all these types of other kinds of software.
So, is it right to think about it as Git-like abilities, but with the ease of use of say a Google Docs or Google Sheets? Yes, exactly.
Got it. All right.
If since the time that this came about, it used to be called local only software, I think back in the days there was one iteration of it called offline first software as well.
What kind of technological improvements have made it easier for developers to adopt this or or have made it possible to be able to resolve conflicts between users, synchronize data, the sync engine and so forth.
What are the sort of key the technological improvement that have enabled local first software to be adopted more?
Yeah, so one of the main things that the sync engine needs to do is to well,
it needs to capture all of the edits that are made to some document or some file and then it needs to be able to merge things if
two different users concurrently edit the same file.
Now, there a few different algorithms which have been developed for this sort of thing.
Google Docs, for example, uses a type of algorithm called operational transformation, which has been around since the early '90s, actually.
So, its approach is able to merge concurrent updates.
So, if different people edit the text on their respective devices, then this algorithm can merge those edits together in a clean way.
But, it does depend on a single central server.
And so, as I just discussed, part of what we're trying to do with local-first is also open the option of not having that one central server.
And there's a different family of algorithms which has been developed which can handle this type of merging and conflict resolution without assuming a server.
And they're called conflict-free replicated data types, or CRDTs.
And this is actually how I got into the whole area, as well.
So, when I first started working on collaboration software in 2015 or so, that was because I had just read the research on CRDTs, which was quite new at the time.
And we didn't yet have the term local-first, and we hadn't yet really worked out these ideas and principles so well, but we did have these algorithms.
And I saw in those algorithms the promise of building a better type of software.
And so, I started then doing research on CRDT algorithms myself.
And initially, that was quite theoretical of just trying to figure out how the merging behavior should actually work, and how we implement it.
And then, over the years, we put a lot of work into the efficiency and performance of these data structures.
And now, gradually, we're getting to the point where we feel like, okay, we actually have a pretty solid set of not just algorithms, but implementations and systems.
But, they're based on this CRDT research from the last decade or two. Got it.
For the interest of the listener, I'm just going to define a few of the terms that you just mentioned.
When you say a sync engine, am I right to understand that it is very hard just making sure that any changes that have been made by a user on their device,
if say the user was offline for a bit, that those are synced with either the central repository central sort of server or with other users whenever the internet connection is back. Is that accurate?
Yeah, so you can think of a sync engine as an embedded database plus a replication protocol, if that's any clearer.
So, an embedded database like SQLite, it works very nicely, but it's you have data only on one device.
If you have like a cloud database like Postgres or so, then you might have multiple replicas of that, but in that case you would typically have one primary replica and then several followers.
And with a sync engine, it's more of a decentralized model where there isn't really one primary copy,
but each user on their local device has a local embedded database that stores the data for that user.
And then, if the user updates it, those updates can then be synced to a copy on other collaborators' devices, perhaps via servers, perhaps peer-to-peer, whatever.
And if other users make changes, then respectively they're synced back to the local user.
So, given that each user has data and when they make changes on their device, it is then synced with all the other users, how do you ensure that the size of the data that's on each device just doesn't grow exponentially?
Because you don't want all users to have information about all other users' data, right?
How do you ensure that the database on each user's device is specific to just what that user needs?
Yeah, so we think Local First is not for absolutely every type of software, but it's particularly good for software where the data is basically all created by the user themselves or by their collaborators.
And so, in that case, the data you need to sync to a user's device are just either the files that that user themselves created or the files that a collaborator chose to share with that particular user.
And so, the way you define what you sync is then through access control essentially.
You look at all the documents that that user should be able to read and write, or maybe just read, and those are the ones you sync.
And so, on the server, if there's a sync server, it may have a much larger collection of documents, but you would only sync to each individual user those docs that that user has access to.
That may still in some cases be a lot of data, and so in that cases you may still want some mechanisms of filtering it down and syncing only subsets.
But that's the core idea of how we're approaching that at least in Automurge.
So, when I say documents here, you can think of that as like a file or a document is just a granular defined grained element at which you can share.
So, you could give access to someone to a document or a collection of documents.
Can you define Automurge, what it does, and sort of where it's used?
Yeah, Automurge, it's a sync engine, or you can think of it as an embedded database that you can run in a browser or inside a mobile app, where it captures any changes that you make to the data.
The data is represented in a JSON-like data model with a few extensions, and anytime if you want to represent, say, a spreadsheet, you would model that spreadsheet as a JSON document.
Every time that somebody edits a cell in the spreadsheet, for example, you would then go in and update the corresponding part of that JSON document that represents that cell,
and Automurge then persists that change to local storage.
So, in a browser that might be to IndexedDB, for example, if it's in a native app that might be just to the file system,
and it also then syncs that data over the network to any other copies, any other users who who have a copy of the same document.
And Automurge handles all of the network communication stuff.
So, there's a network protocol in there that is able to figure out when a user reconnects, what changes do they need to download and upload so that they're in sync with whoever they're syncing with right now.
And to make that efficient, even if you have a large collection of documents, and then while the user is online, any changes that one user make get relayed in real time to their collaborators.
And while the user is offline, any changes they make just get buffered locally on their local storage and then synced to the next time that the user is online.
In an industry where demand for verified skill has never been higher, prove you have the foundation to deliver results
[music]
with the IEEE Computer Society's new software professional certification for emerging professionals.
Give your career the head start it deserves.
Visit computer.org/certification today.
Can you talk a little bit about how this automatic syncing works?
Because there could be changes that if we take an example of say a document, if I make a change when I'm offline and somebody else also makes a change around the same area, is it last in like the most recent changes come first?
How do you decide which changes should be a sort of the final version?
Yeah, so we combine all of the changes together and try to merge them in a way that preserves the intentions of the users as much as possible.
There are of course limitations to what is possible.
So, if two users edit the same word in the same sentence, then the best we can do is well, we preserve all of the inserted characters essentially and make sure that they appear in the right order.
But for example, if you replaced word A with B and I replaced word A with C, then in the final document it will then say BC or CB.
So, both of the texts that we inserted will still be there, but the algorithm doesn't try to do anything clever with, for example, ensuring that the final sentence is grammatically correct or anything like that.
So, it just ensures everybody's in a consistent outcome, and then if that merged outcome isn't what you liked, then you can still edit the document and fix the bad merge.
That's essentially the philosophy that we take here.
So, there's no explicit merge conflict resolution step like there is in Git because we felt that that often leads to like just really complex user interfaces.
You know, everybody using Git hates resolving merge conflicts because it's just so confusing and sometimes mind-bending to figure out how to merge these things.
So, we figured out that what we would rather do is just merge things automatically and then fix things up after the fact if it isn't what was desired,
but the merge algorithm does ensure that if two users independently merge the same changes, then they will end up in exactly the same state.
So, they will then have the same document on their screen at the end.
Good.
So, it takes a first stab at coming up with like a merged version, and if the users find that it's not what they wanted to be, they can go and make additional changes. Is that correct?
That's right. Yes.
What we'd ideally like is maybe some more tooling around helping apps surface conflicts to users.
So, when we've merged edits that are very close together, for example, then it would be nice to maybe show a pop-up to users saying, "Hey, we did a merge here that you might want to review because the edits were very close together."
The trouble is there, how do you define close together?
And so, in a text document, maybe you define close together in terms of how many characters they are apart, but in a spreadsheet, close together may mean something entirely different.
And then in a graphics app, close together may mean something else again.
So, that's a problem that we haven't really cracked yet.
At the moment, we just do the merge and let users review it.
We don't yet have that mechanism for surfacing these potential conflicts to users, but we'd love to have that in the future.
Am I right in thinking about auto merges for it is able to, depending on the file types, be it like a document or a spreadsheet, it saves it as JSON and it is able to manage the changes that each user makes and resolve those conflicts.
For any new file type, is there work required to, you know, enable it within auto merge?
Yes, so you would have to map it onto the data model that auto merge provides, which is this JSON plus a few extensions like I mentioned.
So, you know, that's comparable to if you're building an app on top of a relational database, then you have to figure out how to model your data in terms of tables and rows.
So, there's a similar kind of data modeling process that happens.
The reason we chose JSON is that we found that many client-side apps, front-end apps,
naturally represent their data in a kind of JSON form and that's, if you're using a user interface framework like React,
for example, that kind of data model is is almost assumed that it's really part of the way how these front-end frameworks work.
And also, it's just something that all developers are familiar with.
Everyone can imagine what JSON looks like and so it and and it's a very flexible format.
It allows us to represent ordering, for example, in a way that is harder with a relational model.
So, if you have a a to-do list in which you want your to-do items to appear in a particular order, well, in JSON, that's really straightforward, you just make an array.
If in a relational model, well, you would then have to have some sort of numbering of the rows to tell you in which order they belong and then, as rows get moved up and down, you have to renumber them carefully and that gets a bit messy.
So, the JSON data model seems to work quite well here, but it does assume that you're building your app really on top of the sync engine.
It's a little bit hard to retrofit this to an existing app that doesn't have this kind of data model layer of the same same sort at its core already.
And when you say you it assumes that you build your app on top of the sync engine,
I'm taking I'm understanding that to mean that you're really conscious about how the syncing works and like what you're saying,
when it comes to cases where there are conflicts, the way the sync engine handles the conflict is very specific and the app needs to be cognizant of that and give the user the ability to maybe go back to an older revision or make changes and so forth.
Is that correct?
Well, it doesn't need to be that complex actually.
So, the app doesn't really have to worry about the fact that sync is occurring.
It can just take the state that's represented in this local database and render it.
And we've had some success putting single user apps to be multi-user by putting them on top of automerge.
So, for example,
TLDraw, you know, it is an open-source little graphics browser-based vector graphics tool and we were able to fairly easily put that
on top of automerge by just taking the TLDraw internal data model and mapping it onto an automerge document.
As and it uses a JSON-like model, so that fit well.
And that way we were able to make a a collaborative TLDraw actually quite easily.
And what were some of some of the challenges that you encountered while building automerge?
The biggest challenge has really been performance and memory usage over the years.
And we've put a lot of engineering work into that because the approach how automerge works is you can think of it like a version control system like Git.
So, every time you edit the data in any way, we capture that.
The difference to Git is that automerge is designed for very fine-grained changes because we want to be able to use it for real-time collaboration and people are using it for real-time collaboration.
So, Google Docs style, which means that potentially every single keystroke becomes a commit.
Now, if you use Git like this way, creating a separate commit for every keystroke, it would be ridiculous and extremely inefficient,
but we put a huge amount of work into the internal data structures of Automerge so that we could have a Git-like model, but at the same time represent this very fine-grained editing history.
And like Git, Automerge also retains the full editing history, so that means you can look back at past versions of a document.
You can do a diff of what did your colleague change last week while you were on holiday, any of those kind of things that, you know, we're very familiar with from Git,
but people don't really have those kind of version control capabilities inside other apps.
And so, part of the goal of Automerge, besides providing this tool that, you know, supports real-time collaboration, is actually to try and bring these version control concepts to other types of apps.
But the challenge there has really been in maintaining all of that editing history efficiently.
I think we have some pretty good solutions for that now, but it has taken several years to get there.
And what kind of usage are we talking about in terms of, you know, how many users right now use the library?
Is it used in production systems?
What's the scale like?
We don't really count users in the traditional sense because it's it's not a cloud service.
It's like asking how many users does Postgres have? Well, I don't know.
Yeah, and NPM downloads is a good metric, yeah.
So, apparently there's 14,000 weekly downloads from NPM at the moment.
So, it is being used quite a bit, I would say.
It's obviously still a comparatively new technology, but people are using it for serious stuff.
The number of users doesn't, per se, really make a huge difference.
One of our design goals of Automerge, actually, is at least eventually to be able to support Wikipedia-scale collaboration.
And so, there's no current plans for Wikipedia to adopt Automerge, but if they wanted to, it would be possible.
And so, you know, that's a very large collection of documents with a large number of collaborators.
The challenges that arise with really large number of collaborators are more around the like permissions and the human coordination aspects.
If you have a document that's publicly available on the internet for anybody to edit,
then you'll inevitably have problems with vandalism and people just coming in and defacing it or adding rude content to the document or anything like that.
You know, that's not something that automerge per se can solve.
Automerge is just a a sync engine, so it's not a a moderation system that's designed to solve with those types of things.
But from an automerge level point of view, the number of users that are collaborating doesn't really make a big difference.
So, automerge itself just assumes there's some way for the user to get access to the right documents.
We are working on a cryptographic access control system called Key Hive, which is designed to go alongside automerge.
This is not quite ready yet, so this has been in development for the last year or so.
Um, the idea with this is to have a way of having say Google Drive style permissions, so you could grant somebody access to a folder full of documents,
for example, and then for those individual documents then to become accessible to the user who's been granted access, and you need to be able to revoke access again,
of course, and to be able to have maybe teams of users and be able to grant everybody within a team access, those types of things.
So, doing all of that, but without again relying on a single trusted server.
So, all of these access control things are really easy if you just have a single authoritative server that can decide who gets to access what.
But in a decentralized case where it's potentially peer-to-peer, that becomes a lot harder because you need cryptographic keys in order to identify the users at all of the users' devices.
So, with Key Hive, we create a a separate cryptographic key pair for every device,
and then we have a access control delegation system essentially where the creator for some document can then delegate access to different keys or different groups of keys, and thus grant them access.
And then there's a permission checking system which is able to when you get an edit from somebody for example figure out was that edit actually allowed or not?
Was that edit made by an authorized user?
And that can all be done without assuming a central server.
And then finally Keyhive actually enables end-to-end encryption as well because we have this these cryptographic keys anyway, we can then use that to encrypt the data on any sync servers.
So, the sync servers can't actually see the content of the documents at all, but only the end users on their devices can decrypt the documents in the same way as like Signal and WhatsApp do.
We're essentially trying to bring that kind of end-to-end encryption to file editing as well. Great. I mean I totally really interesting now.
In the interest of time, I think we've spoken a lot about Automerge and it was really interesting to understand how it works.
One point that you mentioned earlier was you know, I think you had mentioned it in passing that local first is not for all kind of software.
There are certain kind of software where it's better suited versus others.
Where do those boundaries lie?
Like what is good for local first and what is really not?
Yeah, I think the apps where local first works really well are the apps where the user can edit the data in whatever way they like.
And so, that's the case with a text editor or spreadsheet or a graphics app, you know, the user can is free to change the data however they like.
With a bank account say, this is not really the case.
If with a bank account, I could edit the bank account balance and add an extra zero at the end, but you know, the bank is not going to pay any attention to my edit because it's not meaningful.
So, for that type of apps, I think you know, if it's managing some real world resource like money or say inventory in a warehouse or something like that,
I suspect that like the traditional cloud model is still more appropriate for that type of app.
And then furthermore, if there's apps with large data sets, so say it's an e-commerce website, in principle you could make that local first,
but that would mean syncing the entire product catalog to every user's local device.
And that's probably not going to make sense because the user's only going to be interested in a a tiny fraction of the product catalog.
They're not going to read every single product description page.
And so in that case, I think the traditional web approach is just fine as well, where, you know, you have an e-commerce website, you just go to the product pages for those products that you're interested in,
you download those individual pages, and you don't download the entire catalog.
So, this pre-downloading everything is really useful if this is data that the user is likely to want to edit offline or access offline.
But in the case of a large product catalog, that doesn't really make sense.
So, you know, I think we want to be sensible about where it applies and where not.
Those are the the heuristics that I use.
To summarize, software that requires like a single source of truth, be it like a financial thing or a stock exchange software, something like that, that certainly will not apply.
Local first will not be applicable.
But for things like say a note-taking software or, you know, or um some sort of a chatting app, anything where user is entering their own data and being able to manipulate that, then it makes more sense.
Exactly. Now, from a developer point of view, in order to build local-first applications, how much do they need to get into the weeds of, you know, the sync engine and CRDTs and all of that?
Is there a complexity tax, really?
For designing something that's local-first as opposed to, you know, just building a very quick app, setting up a cloud database somewhere and a REST API to sort of quickly access it and a client-side app access it.
Is it harder to build something local-first?
So, our hope is that it's actually easier, not harder, and so all of these details of CRDTs is something that app developers should hopefully never have to worry about.
In fact, I think the Auto Merge website barely even mentions the word CRDT because we think that for users, that's just not something that they should have to think about or for app developers.
The only real challenge is just that it's a different model,
and so if you're used to the way of building software for the cloud and you have your tools and workflows and and habits that you've built around that
kind of software architecture, then it requires learning a new model.
And even though that model might be simpler, there is just a bit of a switching cost in learning something new.
So, that's what I see as the main challenge to adoption here.
And when it comes to things like you know, like say for listeners, if somebody wants to experiment with it, how do you recommend they get started?
Is there like an kind of a popular example that folks like to use?
So, if you want to get started with Auto Merge specifically, there's documentation on the Auto Merge website that is hopefully fine for getting started.
There's also a friendly Discord community where you can get questions answered.
If you're interested in local-first more broadly, there's quite a nice website put together by Johannes Schickling from the Local-First podcast.
So, this is on the website localfirst.fm, and if you click in the top menu on landscape,
it has essentially a catalog of technologies for building local-first software, and Auto Merge is included there along with a whole bunch of other tools.
Some are like open-source projects, some are startups, and they don't have all exactly the same design approach.
Some prioritize having a central server and are happy not supporting peer-to-peer, for example, whereas others want to be able to support peer-to-peer operation, and there are various other trade-offs that they make.
Some, for example, retain version history, so you can do version control.
Some are focused more on real-time collaboration and don't retain version history, and so on.
So, there's no, like, as usual with these systems, there's no one right answer for all applications,
but hopefully this local-first landscape can help you figure out what tool would be appropriate for your particular application.
One question that I wanted to ask that I'd missed earlier was we've been spoiled by the likes of big cloud providers, Google and others, to have really good search functionality always there,
so you can you don't realize how good it is, but you're able to search for like one little keyword on millions of documents and it comes out in like less than a second.
If your database is on the device, does the developer is the are they expected to invest time to build really good search functionality to match what they see in the cloud?
Yeah, so with local-first, if you want to search to work offline, then of course your your search function will have to be locally on the client as well.
I think there are some really nice apps that demonstrate how well that could be done, like Obsidian is my new taking app, for example, and it has a great search functionality.
It's super fast.
I have a pretty large collection of notes accumulated over the years, and I'm able to find things within a keystroke.
So, I think, you know, it it will require a little bit of investment, but a server-side searching functionality requires investment as well.
And in fact, scaling a server-side search is probably harder than making a client-side search engine.
So, there are plenty of existing search engines, open-source tools that you can use.
At the moment, we don't yet have a really nice integration of Automerge with search engines.
So, that's maybe something where we could invest in the future.
So, for now, if you're using a sync engine like Automerge, you would then, as updated documents come in over the network, you would need to update the local search index as well.
But that way, you would be able to provide really nice search locally, too.
Understood. This may be a very simple question, but like, if all of the data is stored on a local device, let's say it's a phone, and if I lose my phone, and if I haven't synced to the server in a while,
or if if there wasn't a server, or if it was all peer-to-peer, what happens?
Well, if you've not synced anywhere, then the data will be gone.
And so, part of the reason for having sync servers is also providing a backup mechanism.
And so, we recognize that that's a a useful function that sync servers provide besides just getting the bytes from one device to another.
The backup functionality is is a useful thing, because obviously people do lose devices.
If you're in a peer-to-peer setting, you would probably want something like a backup peer.
So, you could actually still, whether you call it a server or a peer that happens to be online most of the time, it's kind of the same thing.
But that's just inherent if if you haven't copied the data anywhere off device and you lose the device, then of course it's gone.
But I think just the fact that you have the local copy doesn't mean you can't have a cloud backup as well.
Cloud back backups are perfectly fine, and we encourage that, too.
But I think the distinction that you draw is the cloud backup is just like a dumb backup, right?
Like it's an S3 backup. You just put the data there.
You're not relying on the cloud to do any collaboration or to search it or anything.
You're just keeping it there as a way to store it. And Exactly.
Yeah, it's just very straightforward storage.
Understood. Understood.
Switching gears a little bit to the sort of, you know, the compulsory AI question.
With the advent of AI co-coding tools and chatbots, is there a change in the adoption of local first?
Is it making more sense to have, you know, having a local database?
Does it help with running LLMs on your device where you have its own sort of its own memory that can bank on?
How has AI changed local first adoption?
Yeah, the two seem to go together very nicely, actually.
Partly, it's that since Local First enables a simpler application architecture because you're basically only building the front end and you don't need to build the back end,
it becomes easier to actually write code an entire app and have it work because there's just fewer moving parts that need to be coordinated.
So, I think AI-assisted software development is is definitely friendly to Local First because it's this more self-contained programming model.
But, another aspect there is that with AIs, essentially, we can treat human-to-AI collaboration as just another instance of human-to-human collaboration,
and Local First is already all about collaboration.
And so, when we started the Local First thing, AI wasn't big yet, and so we were assuming human-to-human collaboration.
But, actually, we've had really good success applying the same principle for two human-to-AI collaboration.
So, one example of that would be you want to have an AI agent maybe rephrase a text document that you've written.
But, then you probably want to review the edits that that AI has made and check that you actually agree with them.
You don't want those edits just immediately going in.
And so, the way we do that is to use the same kind of versioning control and change tracking facilities as we do for human-to-human collaboration.
We just say, essentially, the AI makes a pull request against your document, and you get to see a diff, and you get to review every change that was made by the AI, accept it or reject it.
And so, this actually This wasn't planned originally, but it seems to have worked out very nicely in the age of AI.
That makes a lot of sense, and it's really interesting cuz you do especially when you're using agents, it goes and iterates so fast, it makes so many changes that the idea of looking back at the revision history doesn't really come up.
It's more like I gave it something, and then it ended up with something else.
And especially if you're if you're going there and then you're sort of making more edits, having that version history and seeing what those changes were is very interesting.
Are there any apps or any groups that are using it or is it still sort of in the experimental stage?
Yeah, there's a bunch of production apps using it.
There's a whole list of products that describe themselves as local first, which I've put together.
I wouldn't be able to name them all off the top of my head because there are literally dozens of products on there.
So, it's really like catching on as an industry trend, I would say.
Given that there's with in any local first app, there's going to be a lot of data being stored in the device itself.
Has anyone tried to use that data as sort of long-term memory for AI agents or for LLMs that are running on the device itself without even going to the cloud?
Like running like a local instance of say Llama.
Yeah, people are experimenting with running local models uh locally on device, and I think that's a really promising direction.
I think right now the biggest and most powerful and and best models are still cloud-based,
but there seem to be enough open-source models that are good enough for a whole bunch of use cases that you can have software that
is able to have uh AI-based facilities working offline, for example, by using a local model, and local first plays into this very directly. A few last things.
If you had to pick one benefit, you know, that'll finally push local first into the mainstream, what would it be?
Would it be speed, privacy, or the fact that the the app won't die or the data won't die if the company does?
I would say different benefits matter to different people, and so I wouldn't say like there's one thing that applies to everybody.
For me personally, I think the one that I care about most is not being dependent on individual providers.
So, I'm very worried about say a provider locking you out because whatever,
some automated system decided that you were violating the terms of service and then if you get locked out of your Google account for example, you have basically no recourse because,
you know, good luck getting a hold of an actual human being at Google.
So, I think this puts us in a very precarious situation with cloud software.
And so for me personally, I think this this knowledge that there's a local copy of the data that nobody can take away from me, that's what matters most to me.
But for other people like maybe the developer experience matters more or the user experience benefits of having software that's really fast.
So, I wouldn't say there's just one single aspect.
That is very interesting. I mean, it's one of those things that you almost take for granted that yes, Google Gmail will always be present.
We'll always have access to that. But you never know.
You never know what forces are there.
There could be like a court ruling against you or anything of that sort which might just suddenly block your access to all of these things.
Which brings up another question though.
We've talked about the technical aspects.
Is there a change in the legal system wherein, you know, do you think we'll see regulations that you see that certain types of data, maybe medical or financial records, should be local first for privacy reasons?
Well, there's already a lot of regulation that requires medical data to be stored locally within the country.
Many countries have this sort of regulation already.
That doesn't imply locally on device necessarily, but it is locality within the country.
So, there's sort of a a similarity there.
I think I'm less concerned about regulation,
but I am a bit concerned about the wider geopolitical So, as we've seen in the last few months for example,
there's been tensions between Europe and the US about Greenland and this has made me quite worried about what if some if these tensions escalate and
Europe is currently highly dependent on US cloud services and what if there's suddenly an executive order that limits European companies access to US cloud services.
And that could happen overnight.
I think the chances of that happening are not very great, and I really hope that it doesn't happen, but I think you know, a year ago it would have been unthinkable, and now it's unfortunately no longer unthinkable.
And so, I do believe that
local-first has a role to play in getting our systems away from this dependency on a single server hosted by a single company in a single country,
and more towards a more decentralized model where you could have multiple servers.
They can be hosted by different companies.
They can be hosted in different countries.
If one of them goes away, it's not a big deal because the others are still there.
So, I think I'd just like to move to this slightly more relaxed model where decentralization actually guards against some of these geopolitical risks.
Yeah, I think it's a great place to leave it.
And it's It also the way that local-first movement also has developed is that you start small, you start thinking about your app, or whatever you're building,
and making sure that if some data doesn't need to be in the cloud, don't put it in the cloud.
If you can manage by just keeping it locally, go ahead and keep it locally, and deal with the problems of syncing it between users as a separate thing.
Keeping it This whole default state where everything starts off in the cloud has all of these risks as you pointed out.
If folks want to know more about your work, where should they go?
Yeah, if they're interested in Automerge as a sync engine, automerge.org is the the website for that.
If they're interested in local-first more generally, I would suggest reading our 2019 essay on local-first software, which is on the Ink & Switch website.
If you're interested in like various different local-first tools, on localfirst.fm, and then click the landscape link in the top menu.
That has an overview of a whole bunch of different products and systems.
Yeah, if you're interested in like academic research, then I have a personal website with a bunch of publications on it as well.
And a new edition of your very popular book is coming out sometime this year, right? Yes, exactly.
So, the print edition should be out within the next week of this recording actually.
So, by the time you listen to it, it should already be out.
Sorry, the ebook should be out and the print edition comes out in March 2026.
That book has been really instrumental in definitely for my career because a lot of learning about you know, data engineering and distributed data applications comes from that.
So, it became like a foundational text for us.
So, it's a real pleasure to have you on the podcast and thank you so much for taking the time today to talk about local first and how folks can get into it. Thank you.
Thanks for the good questions and yes, it's a pleasure talking to you. Thanks, Martin.
Thanks for listening to SE Radio, an educational program brought to you by IEEE Software Magazine.
[music]
For more about the podcast, including other episodes, visit our website at se-radio.net.
To provide feedback, you can comment on each episode on the website or reach us on LinkedIn, Facebook, Twitter, or through our Slack channel at SE-Radio.slack.com.
You can also email us at team@se-radio.net.
This and all other episodes of SE Radio is licensed under Creative Commons License [music] 2.5.
Thanks for listening.